We have now learned
about properties of Petri nets:
the liveness properties
including the question of
freedom from deadlock, and resource
constraint properties, i.e., 1-safety and boundedness.
Other important notions
we will look at
are causality,
concurrency, and conflict.
So we'll be
dealing with those.
This week, though,
only with causality.
So concurrency and
conflict will be postponed
until next week, or
we'll deal with them then.
Then we will have formally summarized almost
all the properties that were discussed informally before.
Questions about general fairness
would then still be open.
But we will not discuss these
in the lecture related to Petri nets.
One difference of these three properties from
the ones we have seen so far
is that these are properties concerning
single transitions in a Petri net.
All the properties about
liveness and about boundedness
were properties of Petri
nets as a whole.
A Petri net is
strongly lively or not.
A Petri net
is bounded or not.
The question of
causality is not:
Is the
Petri net causal?
But there one asks whether
certain transitions in a given
Petri net
have certain properties.
These are properties *in* Petri nets, not
properties *of* Petri nets as a whole.
Let us first consider again the
definition for the first property: causality.
This is defined with reference
to the notion of firing sequences,
which we have already
considered in a previous lecture.
And first defined
formally here it says:
Causality is about whether one transition
is a necessary condition for another.
Causality is, so to speak, the
dependence of one transition on another.
One says, a transition t1
in a given Petri net is
necessary condition for the firing of
the transition t2, if it is
so that t2 cannot be fired,
without that before somehow t1 was fired.
So if for any firing sequence (using
this notation t-serpent) that somehow leads from the
original initial marking to the firing of
t2, the case is that this t-serpent
must in any case contain transition t1, because
otherwise it could not be true at all.
Because we can't
find any other
constellation where t2 is fired
and t1 wasn't fired before.
So if always then
in such a constellation
in any case t1 must
occur in this firing sequence.
Then t1 is called
necessary condition for t2.
Because then we cannot fire t2
without having fired t1 before (maybe
not directly before,
but sometime before).
Of course, this is only interesting
if t2 is a transition that is
reachable at all, that is,
it occurs in the reachability graph.
This would be already the case for
every transition in weakly living Petri nets.
Furthermore, the definition is not interesting
if t1 and t2 are equal.
Sometime, when
t1 is
fireable or t2, sometime is
the first firing for each transition.
It can't have
been fired before that.
So this is interesting for
weakly alive Petri nets or at
least Petri nets where t2
can be fired at all.
As well as only for the
case that t1 and t2 are different.
So this is
the formal definition.
Again, you can
look at the reachability
graph, especially
if it's finite.
So, if we look at
the reachability graph and ask ourselves:
Is t1 necessary
condition for t2?
Then that would be
the case if all nodes
from which t2 is fireable (that is,
every node from which there is a
transition labeled t2) are reachable only
by paths in which t1 occurs.
That is, to be able to
fire t2 in any way, one
must have fired t1 at
least once beforehand, starting from m0.
To be able to check this in the
reachability graph, it would have to be finite.
Then you can
just look at it.
Look at every point where t2
occurs and ask whether the node
from which t2 is fired can also be
reached via paths in which t1 does not occur.
Then t1 would not
be a necessary condition.
Otherwise, t1 would be
a necessary condition for t2.
Let's look at
this with an example.
Here we have a simple Petri
net with four places and four transitions.
And we can
ask whether any transitions
are necessary
conditions for others.
We
can consider:
What is possible
to fire here?
First of all, t1 must
be fired in this Petri net.
And from this it already follows that
t1 is necessary condition for the others.
Every execution which would be
possible would be like this:
One must fire t1, then one
has a token here and here.
After that one can
alternatively fire t2 or t3.
Both are activated
independently of each other.
In any case, this would
result in a token here.
After that, one could
still put a second token
there by the other transition or fire
t4, if necessary at the end also twice.
But what
we already see:
Possible sequences
are t1,t2,t4;
t1,t2,t3,t4; t1,t3,t4; t1,t3,t2,t4;
t1,t3,t2,t4,t4 and t1,t2,t3,t4,t4.
That would be all the
firing sequences that are possible.
And
we see:
In these firing sequences, for example,
t2 never appears without t1 appearing first.
However, t2 does appear
without t3 appearing first.
That is, t1 is
a necessary condition for t2,
but neither t3 is a necessary
condition for t2 nor vice versa.
The t2 and t3 do not depend on
each other, but they do depend on t1.
And of course also t4 as
the last firing transition depends on t1.
So for example you could find
it also for t2 and t3,
but I wrote down here:
t1 is necessary condition for t4.
Let's actually look at this
in the associated reachability graph.
It looks
like this.
You have to believe me that
I have drawn it completely correctly.
And there we
see, for example:
If we look for t4,
t4 occurs in several places, namely
here, here,
here and here.
And if we look at the
corresponding output nodes, in which t4
is activated (that would be this
one, this one, this one and
this one=, then they can only be
reached via paths in which t1 occurs.
Because t1 is the
bottleneck to fire first.
On the other hand, it
is not true, for example,
that every node from which t4 is fireable
is only reachable by paths in which t2 occurs.
So for this node,
for example, it's true.
Here I can fire t4, and
before I did both t1 and t2.
However, there are also
nodes, for example this
one, where t4 is fireable and
where I never executed t2 before.
Then you can't say that t2 is
necessary condition for t4; but t1 is.
So t2 is not
a necessary condition for t4,
because not every firing sequence
that leads to t4 contains t2.
I had just shown
this in the reachability graph.
There was a firing sequence (namely t1,t3)
that was used to reach a node from
which t4 could be fired,
and t2 had not appeared before.
So according to this definition then t2
would not be necessary condition for t4.
And the same
is true for t3.
So also t3 is not
a necessary condition for t4.
Because there are
firing sequences (namely
t1,t2) after which t4 is
fireable without t3 having occurred before.
Here is the
reachability graph again.
You could use it to
check for the other cases discussed
and for all
combinations of transitions:
Is this transition a
necessary condition for that transition?
Of course, this will also
be practiced on other examples.
And finally, a
remark about causality, which
is relevant because this
is an observation that
we will also consider for other
properties such as concurrency and conflict.
Causality is transitive in the sense
that, for example, order relations are transitive.
This should be a
concept at least for the
Komedia students from
the lecture Mathematical Structures.
But probably also to the
other students from other mathematics lectures.
So it's quite obviously true, or
you can deduce from the definition,
that if, for example, t1 is
necessary condition for t2 and t2 is
necessary condition for t3, then t1
is also necessary condition for t3.
So
that continues.
If something is necessary, and
what is achieved by it
is necessary for something else, then also
in that case t1 is necessary for t3.
So to speak, the other
way around is not necessarily true.
So just because t1 is necessary for
t3 and for example t1 is also
necessary for t2, this does not mean that
this t2 in between is also necessary for t3.
In fact, this can also be
considered in the example just seen.
There t1 was necessary for
t2, and t1 necessary for t3,
and also t1 necessary for t4, but
neither t2 nor t3 were necessary for t4.
So this is only valid in this
if-then direction, not in the opposite direction.